Guide to the Lacy Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Lacy Family Papers
1905-2002
RG 223
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(7 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and collected material document the life and work of three generations of the Lacy family. William H. Lacy directed the Foochow Mission Press and, after 1903, the Methodist Publishing House in Shanghai, while his wife Emma Nind Lacy taught at the Anglo-Chinese School in Foochow and elsewhere. Their four sons and one daughter all served as Methodist missionaries in China. Son George Carleton Lacy spent twenty years as general secretary of the American Bible Society in China and became Bishop of the Methodist China Central Conference in 1941. His son, Creighton Lacy, was a missionary to China from 1946 to 1951 and later taught at Duke University Divinity School.
Lacy, Creighton, 1919-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Creighton Lacy, 2008
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
1888 Dec 28 George Carleton Lacy was born in Foochow [Fuzhou], China, son of William Henry and Emma Nind Lacy, Methodist missionaries in China. William H. Lacy directed the Foochow Mission Press and, after 1903, the Methodist Publishing House in Shanghai, while his wife Emma Nind Lacy taught at the Anglo-Chinese School in Foochow and elsewhere. Their four sons and one daughter all of whom served as Methodist missionaries in China. Emma Nind Lacy's mother, Mary Clarke Nind, helped to organize the Woman's Foreign Missionary Society in the North Central states in the U.S. and in the 1890s took a world tour of Methodist mission stations. GCL was educated at mission schools in Foochow and Shanghai
1911 B.A. Ohio Wesleyan University
1913 B.D. Garrett Biblical Institute
1914 M.A. from Northwestern University
1914 Appointed as Methodist missionary to China, arriving in Shanghai in September
1916-1920 After attending the Nanking Language School, GCL was an itinerant missionary in Kiangsi Province, President of William Nast College, and District Superintendent.
1918 Married Harriet Lang Boutelle, who had gone to Canton, China as a YWCA secretary.
1921-1941 Loaned by Methodist Board of Missions to the American Bible Society; served as Secretary of its China Agency and then of the China Bible House formed with the British and Foreign Bible Society. Also served as China correspondent for Zion's Herald and The Christian Century
1928-1929 Studied at Union Theological Seminary and Columbia University in New York while on furlough. Received a second M.A. in 1938. Awarded honorary Doctor of Divinity degrees from Ohio Wesleyan University and Garrett Biblical Institute
1935 Appointed member of the Joint Commission on Unity of the Methodist Episcopal Church and Methodist Episcopal Church, South in China
1941 Elected Bishop of the China Central Conference and assigned to the Foochow area. Traveled extensively in China when his episcopal area was occupied by Japanese troops.
1949 GCL's tenure as Bishop was set to end but the advent of the Communist government made it impossible to hold General Conference or elections. GCL officially resigned and turned his authority over to Bishop W. Y. Chen but he was not granted an exit permit when other missionaries left and was under house arrest.
1951 Died of heart attack while being held at Union Hospital, Foochow.
Biographical / Historical
1919 Jul18 Creighton Boutelle Lacy born in Kuling, China, son of George Carleton and Harriet Boutelle Lacy. He attended Shanghai American School.
1941 A. B. (summa cum laude) Swarthmore College
1944 B.D. (magna cum laude) Yale Divinity School
1944 Married Frances M. Thompson
1944-1946 Pastor of Grace Methodist Church, New Haven, CT
1946-1951 Methodist missionary to China: taught philosophy at University of Nanking, Bible at the Anglo-Chinese College in Foochow [Fuzhow], theology at Union Theological School in Foochow.
1953 Ph.D. Yale University; thesis: "Protestant Missions in Communist China"
1953-1991 Taught missions and social ethics at Duke University Divinity School, served as Associate Dean and editor of the Duke Divinity School Review. His major publications include Conscience of India; Moral Traditions in the Modern World (1965), Frank Mason North: His Social and Ecumenical Mission (1967), The Word-carrying Giant: the Growth of the American Bible Society 1816-1966 (1977), Coming Home--to China (1978)
1991-2010 Professor Emeritus of Parish Ministry at Duke University Divinity School
2010 Oct 8 Died.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, writings, and collected material document the life and work of three generations of the Lacy family. Of particular interest are the missionary circular letters and other documents gathered by Creighton Lacy when preparing his dissertation about Protestant missions and the Chinese church at the time of the Communist takeover. Creighton Lacy also gathered biographical information about the Lacy family and transcribed diaries written by his father, Carleton. Papers related to Creighton Lacy's teaching career at Duke University Divinity School are contained in the Creighton Lacy Papers held there.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1937-2002
II. Writings, 1932-1995
III. Research Files, 1948-1952
IV. Collected Material, 1940-1994
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1905-1997
Missions -- China; Communism and Christianity -- China; Lacy, Creighton, 1919-; Methodist Episcopal Church -- Missions -- China
- Correspondence, 1937-2002; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The letters in Box 1 Folders 5-9 have been digitized and are available under the Lacy Family Papers in the Divinity Library AdHoc Digital Image and Text Database.
  - Carleton Lacy
    - Letters of George Carleton Lacy (GCL) to "My dear Family" written en route to China and from Shanghai, 1937 Dec - 1938 Jan (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - GCL to family from Shanghai, 1938 Feb-1939 Apr (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    - GCL to family, primarily from Foochow, including regarding arrival of Communist army, and regarding activities of Creighton (Corky) who was also in Foochow., 1949 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - GCL to family from Foochow - regular detailed letters regarding his activities following the Communist takeover and regarding activities of Creighton (Corky) who was also in Foochow., 1950 Jan-Dec (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
    - GCL to family from Foochow, including regarding operations of Methodist Church in China, 1951 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - GCL to family from Foochow, including from Union Hospital, including regarding questioning by police, 1951 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Mimeographed circular letters sent by GCL describing his work in China, 1945 Mar - 1950 Jul (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - GCL to/from others: A-J, including Eugene Barnett, William Richard Johnson, 1919-1951 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - GCL and Harriet Lacy to/from others: M-Z, including Carlisle Phillips, 1938-1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence of others, including Methodist Board of Missions, Lucy C. Wang, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Creighton Lacy
    - Letters from his mother in China while he was at Swarthmore; to his father from Swarthmore, to/from uncles and cousins, 1939-1941, 1962, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Circular letter from "Corky" and Fran Lacy while at University of Nanking (1948); letters to CBL, including from Miner Searle Bate, Kenneth Scott Latourette, 1947-1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Writings, 1932-1995; Series II
  - By Carleton Lacy
    - "Lacy-Logues" - 2 printed booklets describing the Lacy family travels in 1932 and 1937; typescript document intended as 1944 sequel to Lacy-Logues, found and edited by CBL in 1995, 1932-1944 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Newspaper article "Aeroplane to Szechuen" from North China Daily News, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Articles: "Creative Imagination", "High Spots in the Central Conference" in The China Christian Advocate; "China, Peace and Propaganda" in The Christian Century; "The Missionary in the Post-war China" (typescript), 1941-1944 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Transcripts of diaries of GCL, including regarding his calling as a missionary, his trip to China, his work in Nanchang, Shanghai, and Kuantseh, Fukien, 1914-1916 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Transcripts/excerpts from diaries of GCL, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Booklet: "Jesus for Chinese Youth" - based on M.A. thesis Union Theological Seminary, Columbia University, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - By Creighton Lacy
    - "Democracy in China" - Honors thesis at Swarthmore College, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
    - Student papers and published articles, including ""The Democracy of China" in Asia and the Americas, "Missions are Missing" in Intercollegian, "Frontiers of Faith" in World Outlook, 1936-1948 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Papers and published articles, including "Christian Missions Confront Communism, 1921-1948", "Five Months to Freedom or Lessons in Liberation", "When Christians Support Marx" in The Christian Century, "The Missionary Exodus from China" in Pacific Affairs, 1949-1958 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Papers and published articles, including "God's Love... Our Mission" in The Reveille, "Christianity and Communism" in Adult Student, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Published articles: "The Banyan Falls" in The American Review, "Motivation for Missions" in The Outlook, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Published article: "Confucian-ism in Mao's China" in International Christian University publication, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Papers and published articles, including in Duke Divinity School publications, 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Papers and published articles, including "A History of Christianity in China" in The China Connection, "My Pilgrimage in Mission" in International Bulletin of Missionary Research, 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Papers and articles, including "China is Young Again: A Student Looks to the Country of his Birth", "The Diaspora from China", response to question "What steps or stages did the Communist regime go through in its treatment of foreign missionaries or missionary institutions?", "A Personal View: The Impact of China on the American Missionary Family" (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Chapters: ""Toward a Theology of Public Responsibility" in America and the Future of Theology; "With Minstrel Heart" in The Hymns of Frank Mason North, 1967, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Study Guides: "Christian Responsibility for the United States and the New Nations", "Adult Guide on Understanding China", "'Adam, Where Art Thou' - Interpretive report of the Interfield Consultation, St. Simons Island, GA, 1956-1969 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - By Others
    - Including writings about China by Harry Haines, Elmer Hall, Betty Hares, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Including writings about China by Virginia Hebbert, Roger Manners, Alden Matthews, Clifford Petitt, 1937-1982 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Including "Interview with Dr. and Mrs. K.H. Ting" by Eugene Stockwell (1976); "Barefoot Through China" by Eugene Stockwell, "Welthy Fisher's Visit to the People's Republic of China" by Sally Swenson (1973), 1973-1980 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Including "Methodist Missionary Contributions to Intercultural Understanding and Diplomacy: The Caldwell Family in Fuzhou and Central Fujian, 1912-1949" by Joseph K.S. Yick, 1979-1993 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Research Files (CBL), 1948-1952; Series III
  - Documentation related to Communism and the Christian colleges and universities in China, 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Missionary circular letters used in preparation of dissertation, "Protestant Missions in Communist China", 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 42-46)
  - Missionary circular letters used in preparation of dissertation, "Protestant Missions in Communist China", 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Statements and writings re. missionary societies and Christians under Communist pressures, 1948-1951 (Box 4, Folder 48-49)
  - Re. Methodist missions in China, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Methodist mission headquarters bulletins, 1951-1951 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Newspapers and magazine clippings, incl.: Time article re. Madame Chiang, Japan-China war, anti-American demonstrations, 1940-1949 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Clippings, incl. re. feud between Stilwell and Chiang, China under Communism, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Clippings, incl. "What Communism is Doing to China"; ""Red Press 'Hate' Campaign; "Christian Chinese Being Slain"; "Reds Deport Missionaries"; "Report on China Missions", 1951 (Box 6, Folder 69-71)
  - Clippings, incl. re. missionaries imprisoned, Christian colleges reorganized under Communists, F. Olin Stockwell and Frank W. Price, others released; Chinese Christian teacher's testimony in a 'self-accusation' meeting; persecution of Chinese Christians, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 72-76)
  - Clippings, incl. re. release of missionaries, Dr. and Mrs. Nathaniel Bercovitz, Dr. Emanuel Gidet, Abbie Sanderson, others; stories of Olin Stockwell and Robert Bryan., 1953 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Clippings, incl. "Red Purge Has Killed 15 Million Chinese"; re. Chou En-lai, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Clippings, incl. "Today in Revolutionary China - How are Christians Faring?"; "Thought Reform in Communist China", 1955 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Clippings, incl. re. release of Wilda and Homer Bradshaw; "My Self-examination" by Wang Ming-Tao; "Church Life in Today's China", 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Clippings, incl. "Red China Makes Swift Progress"; "Mao's War with the Chinese Family", 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Clippings, incl. "China and the UN"; "Chinese Resume Attack on Bible", 1960-1963 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Clippings, incl. "A Struggle to be Faithful"; "Red China Versus the World", 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Clippings, incl. "NCC and Red China", 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Clippings, incl. "The Deification of Mao"; "Mao's Attempt to Remake Man", 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Incl. Quarterly notes on Christianity and Chinese Religion and Culture (Ching Feng); "A Visit to Peking University", 1972 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Clippings, incl. "A History of the Chinese Communist Party, 1921-1949"; "Confucianism Under Attack"; "New Style of Education Emerging", 1973 (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Clippings, incl. "Equality of Women in China'"; "New Cultural Revolution", 1974 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Clippings, incl. "China Revisited"; "Maoism and the Christian Ethic", 1974 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Clippings, incl. "China's Capitalist Troubles"; "Education in China", 1975 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Clippings, incl. "Rewi Alley - 50 years in China"; "China's Emerging New Class", 1976 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Clippings, incl. "U.S. Bishop Died in Red Prison", no date (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Notes: Summaries from books and conferences, 1922-1947 (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Notes: Summaries re. education, Christianity under Communism, etc., 1948-1949 (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - "China Under the Red Flag, WCC paper on Facts and Ideals in Communist China", 1950 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - "The Response of Youth to Communism", 1950 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Notes: Summaries from books, articles, speeches, 1951-1954 (Box 7, Folder 97-98)
  - Incl."Have Chinese Christians Changed Their Thinking Under Communism", 1955-1959 (Box 7, Folder 99-100)
  - Inside China Today; Notes from China Quarterly, 1970-1972 (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - Incl. "American Missionaries in a Turbulent China", 1973-1977 (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Miscellaneous notes, no date (Box 7, Folder 103)
- Collected Material, 1940-1994; Series IV
  - Conference papers and miscellaneous documents related to China collected by CBL, 1994, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 52-53)
  - Booklets: "The Great Migration and the Church Behind the Lines"; "The Great Migration and the Church in West China", 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - First issue of Motive - magazine of the Methodist Student Movement, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Rubbing of Nestorian Stele /Monument with translation (Box OVd-5)
  - Four scrolls (woodcuts): 1) Confucius; 2) Bodhidharma (475-536), the first Buddhist patriarch from INida to settle in China; 3) The "Forbidden City" or Imperial Palace in Beijing; 4) the sacred mountain of Taishan in Shandong Province (Box OVd-5)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1905-1997; Series V
  - Photographs: including portrait of Carleton Lacy (1920), Methodist Bishops at Central Conference (1941), Methodist missionaries in Fuzhou (1950), Commencement, faculty and students of Fukien Union Theological Seminary (1950), 1920-1950 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Northwestern University M.A. diploma of Carleton Lacy, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Biographical statements, obituaries, and tributes to Carleton Lacy, 1951, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 58-59)
  - Birth certificate, grade transcripts, biographical information re. Creighton Lacy, 1919-1995 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Letters and reviews re. Creighton Lacy's book Coming Home - to China, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Letters and genealogical research re. Lacy family, including William Henry and Emma Nind Lacy, 1917-1997, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Documents and genealogical research re. Lacy family and Gamewell family, including re. Mary Clarke Nind, 1905-1994, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 63-65)
  - Bible and devotional book belonging to Mary Clarke Nind (Box 5, Folder 66)